Inventory of the Barnes Family Papers 1797-1926, 1818-1875
Earl Gregg Swem Library, College of William and Mary
Special Collections, Earl Gregg Swem Library, College of William and Mary
Barnes Family Papers, 1797-1926, 1818-1875.
Special Collections, Earl Gregg Swem Library, College of William and Mary
Mss. 39.1 B26
247 items.
Collection contains correspondence, chiefly 1820-1875, of Newman Williamson Barnes and his wife Margaret W.(Tomlin) Barnes of Richmond, Virginia and "Greenfield," Culpeper County, Virginia. Letters concern life in Falmouth, Virginia and also concern Fredericksburg, Virginia. Correspondents are members of the Braxton, Coalter, Tomlin and Oliver families.
Newman Williamson Barnes,; Margaret W. Tomlin Barnes.
Administrative Information
Restrictions on Access
Collection is open to all researchers.
Acquisition Information
Gift: 247 items, 10/16/1938.
Biographical/Historical Information
The following genealogical information is known about the Barnes family. Margaret W. Tomlin and Newman Williamson B. Barnes had the following children: Margaret W., George B., Beverley, Robert Tomlin, Walker, and Lucy Ball. Newman Williamson B. Barnes had the following sisters: Lucy Barnes, Frances C. Barnes, and Balsora Barnes. Other genealogical materials can be found in the "additional related material" section.
Scope and Content Information
Collection contains correspondence, chiefly 1820-1875, of Newman Williamson Barnes and his wife Margaret W.(Tomlin) Barnes of Richmond, Virginia and "Greenfield," Culpeper County, Virginia and to their daughter, Margaret W. Barnes. Letters concern life in Falmouth, Virginia and also concern Fredericksburg, Virginia. Correspondents are members of the Braxton, Coalter, Tomlin and Oliver families. Letters contain social and family news.
Arrangement
Arrangement
The collection is arranged chronologically by date.
Organization
This collection is organized into 9 series: 1. Correspondence, 1810-1829; 2. Correspondence, 1830-1849; 3. Correspondence, 1850-1869; 4. Correspondence, 1870-1930; 5. Correspondence, n.d.; 6. Envelopes; 7. Financial Papers; 8. Newspaper Clipings; and 9. Poetry.
Additional Related Material
Related Material
Additional genealogical information, the Tomlin Family Chart, and other materials related to this collection can be found under the Brown-Coalter-Tucker Papers (I and II), Manuscripts and Rare Books Department, Swem Library, College of William and Mary.
Brown- Coalter-Tucker Papers (I and II), Manuscripts and Rare Books Department, Swem Library, College of William and Mary. 1816-1839,1839-1929.Collection number: Mss. 65 B85 Group C and D.
Index Terms
Family Names:
Barnes family.; Braxton family.; Tomlinson family.; Coulter family.; Oliver family.
Persons:
Barnes, Newman Williamson.; Barnes, Margaret W. Tomlin.
Geographical Names:
Culpeper County (Virginia)--History--19th century.; Falmouth (Virginia)--History--19th century.; Fredericksburg (Virginia)--History--19th century.
Components List
  Series 1: Correspondence, 1810-1829.
- Correspondence, 1810-1829., 42 items. (Box-folder 1:1-42)
  - F[rances] C. B[arnes], Falmouth, [Virginia], to [Newman] Williamson B. Barnes, Richmond, Virginia, 17 Sept. [l8]18., 3 pages. ALS. (Box-folder 1:1)
    Re: disappointed in NWBB's not writing; Lucy, Margaret T[omlin], and Bal[sora] [Barnes] are at Fitzhugh's; have tried to fatten up Judy - Margaret has fattened considerably here; shirts are finished; everyone has been well except Aunt Short; love from Mama and the girls to NWBB and George.
  - Mary [W.] Tomlin, Falmouth, [Virginia], to [Newman] Williamson [B.] Barnes, Richmond, Virginia, 3 Sept. 1820., 3 pages. ALS. (Box-folder 1:2)
    Re: family's four week stay at the Wilderness and the one week visit of Major Jones and family; improvement of Mothers' health; some gentlemen of Fredericksburg serenaded this town last night.
  - Lucy H. Oliver, Frederick, [Virginia], to Newm[an] Williamson [B.] Barnes, Richmond, [Virginia], 18 Sept. 1821., 3 pages. ALS. (Box-folder 1:3)
    Re: arrived at Frederick after a fatiguing journey; Lucy, Nancy, and LHO have been sick with ague and fever; LHO is taking children of deceased aunt to live with her; the children are young and need counsil [sic] and advise.
    Also includes a letter by Lucy Barnes, Frederick, [Virginia], to Newm[an] Williamson [B.] Barnes, Richmond, [Virginia]. Re: LB's health.
  - Lucy H. Oliver, Retreat, [Virginia], to Newm[an] Williamson [B.] Barnes, Richmond, [Virginia], 19 Jan. 1822., 1 page. ALS. (Box-folder 1:4)
    Re: the girls have gone off to spend the day with Mr. and Miss Bassett amusing themselves with toys; should be very much pleased to be agreeably surprised with NWBB's company; had a letter from Lucy saying all are in good health.
  - J[udy] H. Tomlin, Retreat, [Virginia], to [Newman] Williamson B. Barnes, Richmond, [Virginia], 21 Jan. 1822., 3 pages. ALS. (Box-folder 1:5)
    Re: behavior on Sunday has been the subject of the neighbor's discussion since NWBB's departure; has been said that JHT is ill-mannered and rude.
    Also includes a letter by Margaret W. Tomlin, Retreat, [Virginia], to [Newman] Williamson B. Barnes, Richmond, [Virginia]. Re: family news.
  - Frances C. Barnes, [Falmouth], [Virginia], to [Newman] W[illiamson] B. Barnes, Richmond, Virginia, 22 Jan. 1822., 4 pages. ALS. (Box-folder 1:6)
    Re: asks why he has not written his brother; received a letter from Lucy, mentions NWBB's debt, FCB will pay at any time; Mr. George has commenced his school.
    Also includes a note by L[ucy?] H.[?] Barnes, [Falmouth], [Virginia], to [Newman] W[illiamson] B. Barnes, Richmond, Virginia Fragment.
  - Balsora E. Barnes, Falmouth, [Virginia], to Newman W[illiamson] B. Barnes, Richmond, Virginia, 30 Jan. 1822., 3 pages. ALS. (Box-folder 1:7)
    Re: BEB is taking a course in grammar and is pleased with studies - geography, history, chemistry, rhetoric, composition; Cousin Williamson's wedding to Lucy.
  - Judy H. Tomlin, Retreat, [Virginia], to [Newman] Williamson [B.] Barnes, Richmond, [Virginia], 12 Feb. 1822., 3 pages. ALS. (Box-folder 1:8)
    Re: JHT is returning book, please send another; relates gossipy items in a religious text.
  - F[rances] C.. Barnes, Falmouth, [Virginia], to New[man] W[illiamson] B. Barnes, Richmond, Virginia, 16 Feb 1822., 2 pages. ALS. (Box-folder 1:9)
    Re: laments that Mama chose FCB for the topic of her last letter; family news items; wedding at Elwood.
  - Balsora Barnes, Union Academy, [Virginia], to [Newman] [Williamson] [B.] [Barnes], [Richmond], [Virginia], 29 Feb. 182[2]., 2 pages. ALS. Letter fragment. (Box-folder 1:10)
    Re: BB's writing capabilities and responsibilities.
    Also includes a letter by Frances [C.] [Barnes], Union Academy, [Virginia], to [Newman] [Williamson] [B.] [Barnes], [Richmond], [Virginia]. Re: arrival of daughter in family. Also includes incomplete letter.
  - Lucy H. M. Barnes, Eliwood, [Virginia], to N[ewman] Williamson [B.] Barnes, Richmond, Virginia, 19 Mar. 1822., 3 pages. ALS. (Box-folder 1:11)
    Re: family news; Betty is a bright student of Wilson's; we should help make the remainder of our parents' years happy and contented; NWBB's interest in a woman - marriage? - don't keep it a secret.
  - G[eorge] W. Bass[ett], Farmington, [Virginia], to [Newman] Williamson [B.] Barnes, Richmond, [Virginia], 23 Mar. 1822., 3 pages. ALS. (Box-folder 1:12)
    Re: reveals feelings toward women and expresses his dislike for women to have a freedom of expression.
  - L[ucy] H. Oliver, Retreat, [Virginia], to Newm[an] Williamson [B.] Barnes, Richmond, [Virginia], 10 May 1822., 2 pages. ALS. (Box-folder 1:13)
    Re: repair of goods and purchase of goods; an invitation to visit Sunday next.
  - Lucy H. Oliver, Union Hall, [Virginia], to Newm[an] Williamson [B.] Barnes, Richmond, [Virginia], 11 Aug. 1822., 1 page. ALS. (Box-folder 1:14)
    Re: purchase of goods requested and money sent.
  - Lucy H. Oliver, Retreat, [Virginia], to [Newman] Williamson B. Barnes, Richmond, [Virginia], 14 Sept. 1822., 1 page. ALS. (Box-folder 1:15)
    Re: purchase of goods requested and money sent; looking forward to NWBB's visit.
  - [Lucy] H. Oliver, Retreat [Virginia], to Newm[an] Williamson [B.] Barnes, Hanover Town, [Virginia], 14 Jan. 1823., 1 page. ALS. (Box-folder 1:16)
    Re: will give ten dollars to repair the shop; purchase of goods requested.
  - W[illia]m B. Dabney, Richmond, [Virginia], to Newman W[illiamson] B. Barnes, Hanover Town, Hanover Co., Virginia, 4 Sept. 1823., 2 pages. ALS. (Box-folder 1:17)
    Re: arrived in Richmond, NWBB not married yet; other news of activities since being in Virginia
  - Margaret [W.] Tomlin, Union Hall, [Virginia], to [Newman] Williamson B. Barnes, Hanover Town, Virginia, 17 Sept. 1823., 1 page. ALS. (Box-folder 1:18)
    Re: received NWBB's letter; waiting for NWBB's visit; request for shoes.
  - F[rances] C. Barnes, Falmouth, [Virginia], to New[man] W[illiamson] [B.] Barnes, Hanover Town, Virginia, 26 Oct. 1823., 3 pages. ALS. (Box-folder 1:19)
    Re: have been slighted by NWBB not spending any time with us this fall; the fever has been raging in Fredericksburg but not so badly here; travel plans.
    Also includes a letter by Lucy Barnes, Falmouth, [Virginia], to New[man] Williamson [B.] Barnes, Hanover Town, Virginia. Re: have not been in a humor to write; everyone is in good health; anxious to see NWBB.
  - Corbin Braxton, Retreat, [Virginia], to N[ewman] W[illiamson] [B.] Barnes, Richmond, [Virginia], 23 Sept. 1824., 1 page. ALS. (Box-folder 1:20)
    Re: Sarah P. [Oliver] was taken by a fatal chill - instructions on the building of the coffin.
  - Lucy H. Oliver, Retreat, [Virginia], to Newm[an] Williamson [B.] Barnes, Richmond, [Virginia], 30 Sept. 1824., 2 pages. ALS. (Box-folder 1:21)
    Re: the loss of LHO's daughter, Sarah, and LHO's deep sense of grief.
  - Margaret W. Tomlin, Chericoke, [Virginia], to [Newman] Williamson [B.] Barnes, Richmond, [Virginia], 5 Feb. 1825., 3 pages. ALS. (Box-folder 1:22)
    Re: MWT's religious convictions and health.
    Also includes a note by J[udy] H. Tomlin, Chericoke, [Virginia], to [Newman] Williamson [B.] Barnes, Richmond, [Virginia]. Re: thanks NWBB for what he sent.
  - Margaret [W.] Tomlin, Chericoke, [Virginia], to [Newman] Williamson [B.] Barnes, Richmond, [Virginia], 24 Feb. 1825., 2 pages. ALS. (Box-folder 1:23)
    Re: news of the ball; when is NWBB coming over?; please bring goods from Richmond and the 3rd volume of the French Revolution.
  - Margaret W. Tomlin, Chericoke, [Virginia], to [Newman] Williamson [B.] Barnes, Richmond, [Virginia], 5 June 1825., 1 page. ALS. (Box-folder 1:24)
    Re: arrangements for next Sunday.
    Also includes a letter by M[ary] W. Braxton, Chericoke, [Virginia], to [Newman] Williamson [B.] Barnes, Richmond, [Virginia].
  - Judy H. Tomlin, Hybla, [Virginia], to [Newman] Williamson [B.] Barnes, Richmond, [Virginia], 1 Aug 1825., 3 pages. ALS. (Box-folder 1:25)
    Re: have inclination to write to NWBB as frequently as ever; family news, please send several items.
  - Margaret W. Tomlin, Falmouth, [Virginia], to [Newman] Williamson B. Barnes, Richmond, [Virginia], 5 Sept. 1825., 2 pages. ALS. (Box-folder 1:26)
    Re: please tell MWT the whereabouts of the Theatre in Richmond; why hasn't NWBB written to some of us; all of us are very well.
  - Judy H. Tomlin, Hybla, [Virginia], to [Newman] Williamson [B.] Barnes, Richmond. [Virginia], 27 Sept. 1825., 3 pages. ALS. (Box-folder 1:27)
    Re: health of family and neighborhood; newsy items about family.
  - Balsora T. [?] Barnes, Falmouth, Virginia, to [Newman] Williamson B. Barnes, Richmond, Virginia, 3 Oct. 1825., 2 pages. ALS. (Box-folder 1:28)
    Re: newsy items about the activities of friends and relatives including the Pages, Jones, Coalters, Peytons, Brookes,...; mentions good water and pure water in [Falmouth].
  - Judy H. Tomlin, Hybla, [Virginia], to [Newman] Williamson [B.] Barnes, Richmond, [Virginia], 8 Oct 1825., 2 pages. ALS. (Box-folder 1:29)
    Re: fabrics sent and items made from fabrics; please send more flannel, silk, and shoes.
  - L[ucy?] M. H[?] Barnes, Falmouth, Virginia, to [Newman] Williamson B. Barnes, Richmond, [Virginia], 10 Oct. 1825., 3 pages. ALS. (Box-folder 1:30)
    Re: health news; activities of family members and neighbors.
  - Margaret W. Tomlin, Falmouth, Virginia, to [Newman] Williamson B. Barnes,. Richmond, [Virginia], 15 Oct. 1825., 3 pages. ALS. (Box-folder 1:31)
    Re: MWT states her affection toward Willy and how MWT desires his presence.
  - Margaret W. Tomlin, Falmouth, Virginia, to [Newman] Williamson B. Barnes, Richmond, [Virginia], 17 Nov. 1825., 2 pages. ALS. (Box-folder 1:32)
    Re: NWBB's visit to Falmouth.
    Also includes a letter by L[ucy?] H. [?] Barnes, Falmouth, Virginia, to [Newman] Williamson B. Barnes, Richmond, [Virginia]. Re: NWBB's forthcoming visit; LHB places an order for 3 books.
  - Margaret W. Tomlin, Chericoke, [Virginia], to [Newman] Williamson [B.] Barnes, Richmond, [Virginia], 13 Dec. 1825., 2 pages. ALS. (Box-folder 1:33)
    Re: Thanks NWBB for the books, ring, and calico - values the ring most highly; request for additional goods from Richmond.
  - Judy H. Tomlin, Retreat, [Virginia], to [Newman] Williamson [B.] Barnes, Richmond, Henrico Co., [Virginia], 18 Apr. 1826., 2 pages. ALS. (Box-folder 1:34)
    Re: Lucy [Tomlin's] health; JHT's effort to make reconciliation with NWBB.
  - Balsora [Barnes], Retreat, [Virginia], to [Newman] Williamson [B.] Barnes, Virginia, 2 May 1826., 3 pages. ALS. (Box-folder 1:35)
    Re: cousin Lucy's health; forget and forgive for the slight NWBB received on his last visit here.
    Also includes a letter by M[argaret] W. Tomlin, Retreat, [Virginia], to [Newman] Williamson [B.] Barnes, Richmond, Virginia. Re: NWBB's next visit will be a welcomed one.
  - Judy H. Tomlin, Chericoke, [Virginia], to [Newman] Williamson [B.] Barnes, Richmond, [Virginia], 16 May 1826., 3 pages. ALS. (Box-folder 1:36)
    Re: Lucy's improved health; another comment on the argument that occurred that "memorable day - more was construed than was intended.
  - Margaret W. Tomlin, Retreat, [Virginia], to [Newman] Williamson [B.] Barnes, Richmond, [Virginia], 17 May 1826., 1 page. ALS. (Box-folder 1:37)
    Re: sister Lucy's health; NWBB's next visit; orders items from Richmond - fabric, paste-boards, comb, etc.
  - F[rances] C. B[arnes], Falmouth, [Virginia], to [Newman] Williamson [B.] Barnes, Richmond, Virginia, 22 May 1826., 3 pages. ALS. (Box-folder 1:38)
    Re: family news - Lucy's health, NWBB's next visit, etc.
  - Judy H. Tomlin, Falmouth, [Virginia], to [Newman] Williamson [B.] Barnes, Richmond, [Virginia], 27 June 1826., 3 pages. ALS. (Box-folder 1:39)
    Re: Lucy's health; [John] [Tayloe] Lomax has been appointed a professor in the University at Charlottesville; [flood] waters have devastated bridges and other things here; orders fabric from Richmond
  - Margaret W. Tomlin, Falmouth, Virginia, to [Newman] Williamson [B.] Barnes, Richmond, [Virginia], 21 July 1826., 2 pages. ALS. (Box-folder 1:40)
    Re: family news - everyone has been sick.
  - Zach[aria]h Vawles, Falmouth, Virginia, to Newman W[illiamson] B. Barnes, Richmond, [Virginia], 21 July 1826., 3 pages. ALS. (Box-folder 1:41)
    Re: explanation of Vawles' absence when NWBB visited; will make arrangements to pay back money owed.
  - Judy H. Tomlin, Falmouth, Virginia, to [Newman] Williamson [B.] Barnes, Richmond, Virginia, 9 Aug. 1826., 3 pages. ALS. (Box-folder 1:42)
    Re: news of family and activities in the town.
  Series 2: Correspondence, 1830-1849.
- Correspondence, 1830-1849., 54 items. (Box-folder 1-2:43-96)
  - Balsora Barnes, Cumberland, New Kent C[our]t Ho[use], Virginia, to Margaret W. [Tomlin] Barnes, Richmond, Virginia, 13 Mar. 1833., 3 pages. ALS. (Box-folder 1:43)
    Re: health of family members, declares love for George; send news of MWTB's children.
  - Balsora Barnes, n. p., to Margaret W. [Tomlin] Barnes, Falmouth, Virginia, 25 Mar. 1834., 3 pages. ALS. (Box-folder 1:44)
    Re: BB is anxious to get down; shall send Peg a bedstead; news of family activities; had hoped the chimney would be done before BB got home and had wanted to paint the dining room; Willy's visit.
  - [?], Richmond, [Virginia], to [Newman] [Williamson] [B.] [Barnes] ?, n.p., 28 July 1834. (Box-folder 1:45)
    Re: have not written because of sore eyes
  - R[obert] W. Tomlin, Office of Stone Wall Residency, [Stone] [Wall] [Mills], [Virginia], to "Sister" [Margaret] [W.] [Tomlin] Barnes, Jeffersonton Post Office, Culpeper County, Virginia, 28 Aug 1835., 3 pages. ALS. (Box-folder 1:46)
    Re: why has MWTB not written; future visit; business at hand is keeping RWT busy; type of "gal" that is for RWT.
  - Corbin Braxton, Warm Springs, [Virginia], to Margaret W. [Tomlin] Barnes, Jeffersonton, Culpepper County, Virginia, 25 Sept. 1836., 2 pages. ALS. (Box-folder 1:47)
    Re: health and weather; CB is looking forward to getting home from trip.
  - Mary W. Braxton, Hybla, [Virginia], to Margaret [W.] [Tomlin] Barnes, Green Field, near Jeffersonton, Culpepper Co[unty], [Virginia], 3 Dec. 1836., 4 pages. ALS. (Box-folder 1:48)
    Re: birth of MWTB's son and inquires of MWTB's health since; family news,; illness of servants and death of one child.
  - Mary W. Braxton, Hybla, [Virginia], to Balsora Barnes, Falmouth, Stafford Co[unty], [Virginia], 3 Aug 1837., 4 pages. ALS. (Box-folder 1:49)
    Re: health of family members; death of Benedict Crump - thrown from a horse; we're in need of rain and in the midst of a terrible drought.
  - Mary W. Braxton, Lodge, [Virginia], to Margaret W. [Tomlin] Barnes, Green Field, near Jeffersonton, Culpepper Co[unty], [Virginia], 19 Aug. 1837., 4 pages. ALS. (Box-folder 1:50)
    Re: sorry to hear MWTB's been sick; MWB's happiness depends a great deal on that of her sisters and brothers; it has not been pleasant since the girls left home; health of family members.
  - L[ucy] M. B[arnes], n.p., to Margaret W. [Tomlin] Barnes, Greenfield, [Virginia], 21 Aug. 1837 [?]., 2 pages. ALS. (Box-folder 1:51)
    Re: Willy's illness and health news of other family members.
  - Mary W. Braxton, Chericoke, [Virginia], to Margaret [W.] [Tomlin] Barnes, Falmouth, Stafford Co[unty], [Virginia], 25 Nov. 1837., 4 pages. ALS. (Box-folder 1:52)
    Re: MWB is worried about MWTB's health; MWB understands that MWTB is coming to Falmouth to see Dr. Buck about her spine; insists that MWTB stay with MWB.
    Also includes a letter by Bal[sora] [Barnes], Chericoke, [Virginia], to M[argaret] [W.] [Tomlin] Barnes, Falmouth, Stafford Co[unty], [Virginia]. Re: family news.
  - R[obert] W. Tomlin, Office of Stone Wall Residency, Stone Wall Mills, Virginia, to "Sister" [Margaret] W. [Tomlin] Barnes, Jeffersonton Post Office, Culpeper County, Virginia, 1 Dec. 1837., 2 pages. ALS. (Box-folder 1:53)
    Re: message to Willy; interested in MWTB's health; love matters [affairs] - RWT has asked two or three demoiselles to be Mrs. Tomlin but all have declined; will see MWTB on the eve of the 13th.
  - R[obert] W. T[omlin], Stone Wall Residency, [Stone Wall Mills], Lynch[bur]g, Virginia, to "Sister" [Margaret] W. [Tomlin] Barnes, care of Balsora Barnes, Falmouth, Virginia, 4 Apr. [18]38., 3 pages. ALS. (Box-folder 1:54)
    Re: RWF's opinions of physicians of the day - compares RWT's profession with that of the physician; gives news of a lass' marriage.
  - Nancy [fl, Chericoke, Virginia, to Balsora Barnes, Falmouth, Virginia, 3 June 1838., 4 pages. ALS. (Box-folder 1:55)
    Re: Cousin St. [George] [Tucker] [Coalter]'s health and Nancy's; family news.
    Also includes a letter by J[udy] H. [Tomlin] Coalter, Chericoke, [Virginia], to Balsora Barnes, Falmouth, Virginia Re: Mr. C[oalter]'s health; instructions on what to do at the house.
    Also includes a note by B[alsora] B[arnes], n.p., to [?].
  - L[ucy?] H. [?] Barnes, Falmouth, [Virginia], to [Newman] Will[iamson] [B.] Barnes, Greenfield, [Virginia], 31 July 1838., 2 pages. ALS. (Box-folder 1:56)
    Re: sending the horse over for NWBB to please take care of; would like to visit but health is poor.
  - Mary W. Braxton, Chericoke, [Virginia], to Margaret [W.] [Tomlin] Barnes, Green Field, near Jeffersonton, Culpepper Co[unty], [Virginia], 15 Sept. 1838., 4 pages. ALS. (Box-folder 1:57)
    Re: health of all; domestic responsibilities - made pickles, catsup, etc; the drought is gone; describes MWB's dear little baby; family affairs.
  - Balsora Barnes, n.p., to Margaret W. [Tomlin] Barnes, Greenfield, Culpeper [County], [Virginia]. 3 pp. ALS. 4 Feb. 1839., pages. ALS. (Box-folder 1:58)
    Re: "Peg's" education; family matters.
    Also includes a letter by Balsora Barnes, n.p., to "Peg" [Margaret] [W.] [Barnes], Greenfield, Culpeper [County], [Virginia]. Re: advice on going to school.
  - Lucy Oliver, Old Church, Virginia, to [Margaret] W. [Tomlin] Barnes, Falmouth, Virginia, 28 Apr. 1839., 2 pages. ALS. (Box-folder 1:59)
    Re: LO's looking forward to a visit from MWTB and the children.
  - Mary W. Braxton, Chericoke, [Virginia], to Margaret [W.] [Tomlin] Barnes, Greenfield, near Jeffersonton, Culpepper Co[unty], [Virginia]., 25 June 1839., 4 pages. ALS. (Box-folder 1:60)
    Re: health of family members; news of the wedding of MWB's daughter, [Lucy?] Braxton, to Dr. [Charles] Cocke - with details of dresses, food, etc.
  - Mary W. Braxton, Chericoke, Virginia, to Margaret [W.] [Tomlin] Barnes, Greenfield, near Jeffersonton, Culpepper Co[unty], [Virginia], 21. Oct. 1839., 4 pages. ALS. (Box-folder 1:61)
    Re: events of MWB's trip to Vaucluse [?]; family news concerning health; well-being and death of members.
  - [Mary] W. Braxton, Chericoke, [Virginia], to Margaret [W.] [Tomlin] Barnes, Green Field, Jeffersonton P. 0., Culpepper Co[unty], [Virginia], 7 May 1840., 4 pages. ALS. (Box-folder 1:62)
    Re: Lucy and Charles Cocke had a baby boy who died in its birth, thankful for Lucy's survival, she is slowly recovering; new s about crops and animals; general family news.
  - R[obert] W. Tomlin, Balcony Falls, [Virginia], to "Sister" [Margaret] W. [Tomlin] Barnes, Jeffersonton p. o., Culpeper County, Virginia, 9 May 1840., 3 pages. ALS. (Box-folder 1:63)
    Re: news of family members; Harry has bachelor, quarters and desires a wife; RWT is living within seven miles of Natural Bridge -Mountainous district is prettier than Tidewater; RWT is having a celibacy existence.
  - [?J. M[argaret] W. B[arnes], Falmo[u]t[h], [Virginia], to "Papa" [Newman] [Williamson] [B.] [Barnes], Greenfield, [Jeffersonton P. 0.], [Culpeper County], [Virginia], 29 May 1840., 4 pages. ALS. (Box-folder 1:64)
    Re: celebration of the Queen of May day.
    Also includes a letter by B[alsora] B[arnes], [Falmouth], [Virginia], to M[argaret] W. [Tomlin] Barnes, Greenfield, [Jeffersonton P. O.], [Culpeper County], [Virginia]. Re: additional details about the celebration of the Queen of May day.
  - Margaret [W.] Barnes, Falmouth, [Virginia], to "Mama" [Margaret] W. [Tomlin] Barnes, Greenfield, Culpepper C[oun]t[y], [Virginia], l[?] June 1840[?]., 1 page. ALS. (Box-folder 1:65)
    Re: why hasn't MWTB written; MWB wants to know news of health of MWTB and NWBB; tells of Aunt Lucy's and MWB's colds; Aunt Fanny and sister's visit to Fredericksburg to hear Doctor Plu[?] and Doctor Alexander preach.
  - W[illia]m Browne, Fred[ricksbur]g, [Virginia], to [Margaret] [W.] [Tomlin] Barnes, Falmouth, [Virginia], 24 Oct. 1840., 3 pages. ALS. (Box-folder 1:66)
    Re: MWTB's health and possible remedies for a cure.
  - R[obert] W. T[omlin], Balcony Falls, [Virginia], to "Sister" [Margaret] W. [Tomlin] Barnes, Jeffersonton p. o., Culpepper County, Virginia, 21 Nov. 1840., 4 pages. ALS. (Box-folder 1:67)
    Re: winter's effect on people; RWT's attitude toward romance.